Fernando Guillen

Berlin Metropolitan Area



fguillen.mail@gmail.com



linkedin.com/in/fguillen

Summary

Full-stack web developer, primarily using Ruby on Rails and associated technologies.

I am a specialist in getting technology products off the ground, from design idea to fully functional application. Focus on production quality, but also on fast feedback loops: deliver fast and iterate. On this role I have worked for start-ups, big companies and also on personal entrepreneurial projects. As an "individual contributor" or as part of a small or large engineering team, as a senior developer or leading architecture decisions.

Most recently in my role as a Co-founder and CTO of a fast growing technology company, I was hands-on directing the implementation from scratch of an architecture that now supports more than 100K requests/min and a business of 8 figures. Leading the technology decisions of a team of ~80 members.

I primarily work on Rails applications, but have a solid exposure to the full web development stack.

At one time or another, I have been in charge of: prototyping, implementing deployment CI based processes, cloud based servers administration, working on or directing scrum teams, working hand by hand with the product team, suffering the hell of having to make C level decisions, microservices, high load traffic, fraud prevention, performance monitoring, autoscaling, terabytes sized DBs, APIs design, ...

I've also had plenty of exposure to different languages including python, C#, Java. And of course most of the modern JS frameworks like React and VueJS.

... But Ruby is what I enjoy working the most.

I am not just a developer, I have sensibility for the business needs, I know when to make compromises, when to cut corners, when to offer alternatives. I am used to working elbow to elbow with the product, sales and leader teams.

I have had the luck of having been always surrounded by incredibly well talented people. I have learned everything I know from them. I owe everything I know to the people of the teams I have worked in, to the community around open source, web development in general and Ruby in particular.

Experience



Technical Products Developer

Freelance

May 2021 - Present (3 months +)

Full-stack web developer, primarily using Ruby on Rails and associated technologies.

I am a specialist in getting technology products off the ground, from design idea to fully functional application. Focus on production quality, but also on fast feedback loops: deliver fast and iterate. I have worked for start-ups, big companies and also on personal entrepreneurial projects. As an

"individual contributor" or as part of a small or large engineering team, as a senior developer or leading architecture decisions.

(b) CTO / Co-Founder

Dalia Research

Oct 2013 - May 2021 (7 years 8 months)

I am the CTO and one of the co-founders at Dalia and my key responsibility is to create a great technical architecture that is easy to work with and that is capable of rapidly adapting to the business needs.

I am part of the Engineering Teams (Development, Data Science, DevOps and Quality Assurance, among them I am mostly focused in the Development sub-team).

I participate in any initiative that requires technology support. Including technical advice, high level strategic technical decisions, technical architecture design, inter product technical dependencies, third-party technologies integrations.

I am involved in any management-related initiative related to Engineering.

I also participate in giving strategy consulting support for business high perspective initiatives.

As one of the co-founders I am also part of strategic initiatives decisions.



Sennior Web Developer and GNU/Linux Administrator

Grupo Planeta

Jan 2003 - Oct 2013 (10 years 10 months)

Hired as web developer to build a technology service to handle the stock of the 50 libraries spread out over all Spain territory (https://www.casadellibro.com/). Replacing the previous system based on Cobol.

My tasks was to study the old system, to understand the new needs the new system should be able to provide and to implement the web based solution.

The delivered system was immediately adopted for all the managers of the 50 libraries. Reduced the time making inventory to 50% and generated and increase of revenue to the whole company due to the recommendations algorithms and the aggregated purchasing mechanisms.

Very soon after my incorporation to the team I was asked to replace the old web servers based on Windows machines to Linux. Implementing load balancing and servers fallbacks. Not any blackout happened during the 10 years I was in charge of these servers.

During my long period in this company I was in charge of the technical implementation of all advance web projects. Including a digitalización of one of his more advance enciclopedias the "Enciclopedia Espasa" (https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Enciclopedia_universal_ilustrada_europeo-americana). The printed version has more than 165,000 pages and 200 million words and over 1,000,000 articles. The system was digesting all XML entries, applying media files and indexing all information using highly equalised Lucene indexes.

Member

SpainRB.org (Ruby Developers Group)

Jun 2009 - Jun 2013 (4 years 1 month)

During my stay in Madrid, when I started to get in touch with Ruby I participated actively in the Madrid Ruby community. I organized community meetups and participate in the organization of conferences as the "Conferencia Rails", the most popular Spanish Rails conference.

Freelance Web Developer

Fernando Guillen

Jan 2008 - Jun 2013 (5 years 6 months)

I am a solutions provider. I deliver technical products that improve the business of my clients. I participate in all phases of the project creation from the description of the need to the production delivery and business metrics analysis.

I have a long experience understanding the business needs and providing solutions adapted to the budget, time and scope.

On top of all, I consider my self a business partner of my clients and my focus is in provide solutions that match the needs of the business.

IT Team Lead

AppBounty

Oct 2012 - May 2013 (8 months)

Taking care of the technology decisions, implementing the backend, defining the deployment process, coordination of the IT resources. Working side by side with the product team. Making real, in a technological perspective, the CEO vision.

Appbounty was a spin-off from a big ad-tech company. Thanks for the good CEO vision and the very good management of the technical resources the project moves in six months from a pet-project from a big company to a very profitable product generating 6 figures dollars per month.

🧲 Senior Web Developer

Fyber — A Digital Turbine Company

Oct 2010 - Mar 2012 (1 year 6 months)

Ruby Sennior developer in a very hard-core Ruby team. High traffic, big data, very complicate business logic, big project ecosystem.

Senior Web Developer

La Coctelera

Feb 2008 - Oct 2009 (1 year 9 months)

Senior Web Developer working in this wonderful and passionated team that is the developers of the most known ruby on rails web 2.0 site in Spain.

It is the boom of the Web 2.0. I was starting to work with Ruby and I decided to work with the most advance company working with Ruby on Rails at that moment in Spain.

It was a baptism of fire. I had the pleasure to work elbow with elbow with the most brilliant minds working with Ruby in Spain. With many of them I still keep profesional and personal contact.

In the project I was in charge in improving or implementing many user faced functionalities like: comments, wysiwyg web editor, moderation mechanism, ... on one of the most popular blog sites in Spanish.

CTO / Co-Founder

Constela Networks

Jan 2005 - Jan 2008 (3 years 1 month)

We are 3 Java engineers, we created a IT consulting company. We managed to grow the team to 8 people and generate 0.5M€ per year.

I was in charge of the IT department attending the key clients needs and dealing with the most IT challenging tasks like big Jave developments and high performance Linux servers maintenance.

Technology Project Boss

Kroonos

Jan 2007 - Dec 2007 (1 year)

I had the pleasure to management and coordinate the developer team of this social web, from the born of the idea until its start on production.

White label community manager built in Java. Totally parametizable, using templates, management functionalities, roles, ...

Used in production to create Kroonos a time bank that was popular in Spain 15 years ago.

Education



Design and Arts High Studies on Logroño

Arts, design

1993 - 1997

My background is not in IT but in arts. It happened that I was good with computers since I was a kid and I managed to combine my creativity with my technical skills to unified both in the technical products I built.

Skills

Ruby on Rails • Ruby • Web Development • Web Applications • Agile Methodologies • Open Source • Git • Linux • JavaScript • SQL